Guide to the
Brown University Library
- The Lounger: Prescott, 1859; 1 page (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 40)
  Newspaper clipping of an obituary for William H. Prescott (1796-1859), an American historian specializing in Spanish history.
  Prescott, William Hickling, 1796-1859
- The Late William H. Prescott, 1859; 1 page (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 40)
  Sketch of a bust of William H. Prescott, printed sometime after his death and clipped from a newspaper.
- Mr. Prescott's Writing-Case, 1859; 1 page (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 40)
  Sketch clipped from a newspaper of a hand holding a pen and position to write, identified as that of William H. Prescott. Presumably printed after Prescott's death in 1859.
- Prescott, William H. to Mariotti, L.Boston, MA, 1840 July 28; 2 pages; Prescott, William Hickling, 1796-1859 (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 41)
  Prescott congratulates Mariotti on having settled back in his native Italy, recalling Dante's observation about the "hard lot of those who eat the bread of exile." He goes on to thank Mariotti for taking on the project of translating his History of Ferdinand and Isabella into Italian, and provides instructions for Mariotti to acquire a copy from his London bookseller, James Rich, Esq. Prescott has included various "errata and addenda" that he had prepared for the next English edition of the volume, inviting Mariotti to include them in the Italian translation: he worries, though, that certain passages about religion and politics "may require pruning for the meridian of Italy." ("Mariotti" was the adopted name of the Italian literary scholar Antonio Gallenga.)
  Ms 599
  Gallenga, Antonio Carlo Napoleone, 1810-1895; Rich, James
- Mr. Prescott's Method of Writing Boston, MA, 1859; 1 page (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 41)
  Newspaper clipping of an article from the Boston Transcript, describing in detail William H. Prescott's daily work habits. Particular attention is paid to how he overcame his limited eyesight in order to achieve success as an historian. Published after Prescott's death in 1859.
- An hour before the fatal stroke Boston, MA, 1859; 1 page (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 41)
  Newspaper clipping of a short article from the Boston Evening Post[?] describing the last hour of the historian William H. Prescott's death. Attention is given in the last paragraph to the expected fate of Prescott's works in progress.
- Prescott, William H. to Mariotti, L.Pepperell, MA, 1840 October 9; 3 pages; Prescott, William Hickling, 1796-1859 (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 42)
  Expresses his regret that Mariotti has again migrated out of his native Italy and his further regret that Mariotti will no longer be able to translate Prescott's History of Ferdinand and Isabella as previously arranged. He thanks Mariotti for the work he contributed to the new edition of the volume and gives Mariotti instructions to obtain a copy of the book for himself from Prescott's London bookseller as a token of appreciation. Prescott indicates that he will now ask Gino Capproni (Italian writer and politician) to do the translation, and he includes a note for Mariotti to forward to him. ("Mariotti" was the adopted name of the Italian literary scholar Antonio Gallenga.)
  Ms 600
  Gallenga, Antonio Carlo Napoleone, 1810-1895; Caproni, Gino
- Prescott and His Labors, by The Professor, 1859; 2 pages (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 42)
  Newspaper clipping of a tribute to the late William H. Prescott, with particular attention paid to his "History of the Reign of Ferdinand and Isabella the Catholic." A brief genealogical diagram for Prescott is provided at the end of the article.
- Death of Mr. Prescott New York, NY, 1859 July 3; 1 page (Box 10, Volume 4, Pages 42-43, tucked between pages)
  Newspaper clipping from the New York Times containing the written address given by George Bancroft to the [New York] Historical Society in memory of the late William H. Prescott.
  Bancroft, George
- Meyrick, Samuel to Mariotti, L.Herefordshire, England, 1840 December 31; 1 page; Meyrick, Samuel Rush, 1783-1848 (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 43)
  Sir Samuel Meyrick agrees to give Mariotti a tour of his castle, Goodrich Court, at Herefordshire and show him the building's "antiquities," citing a complimentary introduction made on Mariotti's behalf by a Mr. Neale. ("Mariotti" was the adopted name of the Italian literary scholar Antonio Gallenga.)
  Ms 601
- A once famous correspondent London, England, 1895 December; 1 page (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 43)
  Obituary from the London Times for Antonio Gallenga, identified as a giornalist, writer, Italian patriot, and member of the Piedmontese and Italian paliaments. Many of his writings were published under the pseudonym "L. Mariotti."
- Meyrick, Samuel to Mariotti, L.Herefordshire, England, 1841 January 13; 3 pages; Meyrick, Samuel Rush, 1783-1848 (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 44)
  Pertains to information that Mariotti has helped to provide about some of the Venetian antiques in Meyrick's castle, Goodrich Court. ("Mariotti" was the adopted name of the Italian literary scholar Antonio Gallenga.)
  Ms 602
- Meyrick, Samuel to Mariotti, L.Herefordshire, England, 1841 February 20; 2 pages; Meyrick, Samuel Rush, 1783-1848 (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 45)
  Thanks Mariotti for an insight he had about some of the antiques in the collection at Meyrick's castle, Goodrich Court. Cites additional information about the collection he has found through research. ("Mariotti" was the adopted name of the Italian literary scholar Antonio Gallenga.)
  Ms 603
- Everett, E. to Mariotti, L.London, England, 1841 November 20; 1 page; Everett, Edward, 1794-1865 (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 46)
  Arranges social call with Mariotti at Everett's London residence. ("Mariotti" was the adopted name of the Italian literary scholar Antonio Gallenga.)
  Ms 604
- Symonds, Henry to [unknown]Exeter, England, 1841 November 20; 3 pages; Symonds, Henry (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 47)
  Regrets that he was unable to show Mr. Mariotti-Gallenga around Oxford University during his visit. Speaks of Mr. Mariotti's interest in the open Italian professorship at Oxford and hopes that he will be able to exert some influence at Oxford on Mariotti's behalf. ("Mariotti" was the adopted name of the Italian literary scholar Antonio Gallenga.)
  Ms 605
- Everett, Edward to Mariotti, L.London, England, 1841 November 22; 2 pages; Everett, Edward, 1794-1865 (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 48)
  Expresses his esteem for Mariotti's "high qualifications" for the position of professor of Italian language and literature at Oxford and wishes Mariotti luck in obtaining the post. ("Mariotti" was the adopted name of the Italian literary scholar Antonio Gallenga.)
  Ms 606
- Mr. Everett's eulogy on Prescott, 1859; 3 pages; Everett, Edward, 1794-1865 (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 48)
  Newspaper clipping of the eulogy for William H. Prescott delivered by Edward Everett at a meeting of the Massachusetts Historical Society in Boston.
- Meyrick, Samuel to Gallenga, Antonio M.Herefordshire, England, 1841 November 23; 1 page; Meyrick, Samuel Rush, 1783-1848 (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 49)
  Accompanies letter from Mr. Henry Symonds of Oxford. Promises to look into the date of death of Michael Angelo Taylor. Commends Gallenga for insisting upon his "freedom of conscience," noting that it would be "hard indeed" for Gallenga to be "fettered" in England after having left Italy to seek freedom.
  Ms 607
  Taylor, Michael Antonio; Taylor Institution
- Everett, Edward to [Gallenga, Antonio M.]London, England, 1841; 2 pages; Everett, Edward, 1794-1865 (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 50)
  Encourages Gallenga to write to "Dr. Hawtrey, Head Master of Eton College, near Windsor," promising him that he is likely to receive a "kind answer." Notes that he has spoken to two people about taking lessons with Gallenga and inquires as to whether lessons are held at Gallenga's residence or the learner's.
  Ms 608
- Meyrick, Samuel R. to Gallenga, Antonio M.Goodrich Court, Herefordshire, England, 1841 December 16; 3 pages; Meyrick, Samuel Rush, 1783-1848 (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 51)
  Regards the difficulty Gallenga is having in obtaining a position as Professor of Italian at Oxford. Meyrick speaks in particular about the "bigotry, prejudice, and illiberality" among the university's administration. He hopes that once the Dean and Vince Chancellor read Gallenga's book, "the liberality of sentiment it contains with respect to religion, will make them either doubt your being a Catholic, or conclude that you are by no means a rigid one." Further advises Gallenga to go to the Prerogative Office to obtain further information about the last will left by the late Michael Antonio Taylor, regarding the creation of a professorship in Italian.
  Ms 631
  Gallenga, Antonio Carlo Napoleone, 1810-1895; Taylor, Michael Antonio; Taylor Institution
- Meyrick, Samuel R. to [Gallenga, Antonio M.]Goodrich Court, Herefordshire, England, 1842 February 21; 3 pages; Meyrick, Samuel Rush, 1783-1848 (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 52)
  Sympathizes with Gallenga's difficulty in obtaining a position at Oxford, praising his courage in the midst of his suffering and connecting Gallenga's experience to Italy's struggles under "despotism." Includes a citation from John Milton: "Better to resign in Hell, than serve in Heaven." Regrets that he no longer has enough influence at Oxford to help Gallenga's case, but encourages him to continue looking into the university's precedents, because it is by precedent that "bigots" such as those managing Oxford, "are generally bound." Promises to be in touch if he hears anything pertaining to the "Taylorian Institution" in London. (Presumably refers to the will of Michael Antonio Taylor, pertaining to the creation of an Italian professorship, mentioned in previous letters in this series. On the topic of disappointing wills, Meyrick here cites Lord Burghersh [John Fane], Gallenga's "patron" and the Earl of Westmorland, who was "sadly disappointed by the capricious will of his father.")
  Ms 632
  Gallenga, Antonio Carlo Napoleone, 1810-1895; Westmorland, John Fane, Earl of, 1784-1859; Taylor Institution
- Everett, Edward to Mariotti, L.London, England, 1843 July 31; 2 pages; Everett, Edward, 1794-1865 (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 53)
  Recounts his recent visit to Oxford, during which he asked Philip Wynter, Vice-Chancellor of the University, about Mariotti's application for a professorship in Italian. Wynter spoke favorably about Mariotti's qualifications, "but said he thought it would be deemed expedient not to appoint any person of the Roman Catholic Church." Includes a final note about Oxford's Taylor College, which Everett does not expect to go into operation in the near future. ("Mariotti" was the adopted name of the Italian literary scholar Antonio Gallenga.)
  Ms 609
  Gallenga, Antonio Carlo Napoleone, 1810-1895; Wynter, Philip, 1793-1871; Taylor Institution
- Silvester [illegibile initial], to Mariotti, L.Beverley, England, 1843 August 17; 1 page (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 54)
  Expresses his hope that Mariotti will receive his money from a Dr. Worthington and will then be able to spend some time on vacation in Beverley. ("Mariotti" was the adopted name of the Italian literary scholar Antonio Gallenga.)
  Ms 610
- [unknown] to Mariotti, L., [undated]; 2 pages (Box 10, Volume 4, Pages 54-55, tucked between pages)
  Invitation to tea, addressed to "Mariotti," the adopted name of the Italian literary scholar Antonio Gallenga.
  Ms 613
- "V. amico" [illegible] to Mariotti, L., 1843 September 1; 2 pages (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 55)
  Reports back to Mariotti about a conversation he had with "quella Signora" about something Mariotti had asked him. Also mentions a letter from a certain Pepoli about the same subject. ("Mariotti" was the adopted name of the Italian literary scholar Antonio Gallenga.)
  Ms 611
- Gibson, Th. Milner to Marrioti, L.London, England, [year unknown] September 21; 3 pages; Gibson, Thomas Milner, 1806-1844 (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 55)
  Invitation to Marotti to call upon the letter's author and see their work. ("Mariotti" was the adopted name of the Italian literary scholar Antonio Gallenga.)
  Ms 612
- Gibson, Th. Milner to Marrioti, L.Hardwick House, Suffolk, England, [year unknown] December 17; 12 pages; Gibson, Thomas Milner, 1806-1844 (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 56)
  Opens by thanking Mariotti for his previous letter, which helped to stimulate and comfort Gibson in his "loneliness," as he is now living far from his friends. Gibson provides a brief account of his daily life, including family rituals on Sunday: here he favorably remembers "[Giuseppe] Mazzini's Sunday lecture to his prophets," contrasting Mazzini's spirituality to what Gibson deems the unfavorable qualities of the established Church. The bulk of the letter is dedicated to an account of Gibner's being in court recently when several individuals were sentenced to death for committing or being an accessory to murder: he provides a detailed description of the pain of watching one man in particular being sentenced to death: how the man bowed his head, how his wife fainted. Death, Gibson insists, is a terrible thing, especially when it comes suddenly in youth, and when it carries blame, as in the case of criminal execution. Gibson notes that he was "sick at heart" when he left the court room. The letter then concludes with Gibson's plans for coming to town and with light social chatter about one of his and Mariotti's common acquaintances. The letter is written on stationary bearing the name "Arethusa," the name of Gibson's wife. ("Mariotti" was the adopted name of the Italian literary scholar Antonio Gallenga.)
  Ms 614 (1), (2), and (3)
  Gallenga, Antonio Carlo Napoleone, 1810-1895; Mazzini, Giuseppe, 1805-1872
- [illegible] to [Gallenga, Antonio M.]Nottingham, England, 1845 July 11; 4 pages (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 57)
  Relates to Gallenga's efforts to get his scholarship published in an English quarterly magazine. Includes some discussion about reception of foreigners in English scholarly circles. Also includes refererence to the Italian writer Foscolo.
  Ms 615
  Gallenga, Antonio Carlo Napoleone, 1810-1895; Foscolo, Ugo, 1778-1827
- [illegible] to [Gallenga, Antonio M.]Nottingham, England, 1845 July 24; 4 pages (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 58)
  Discusses [Henry Wadsworth?] Longfellow's recent work on Dante, in addition to efforts at distributing another copies of another volume ("the Peintures?), with which Gallenga is involved.
  Ms 616
  Gallenga, Antonio Carlo Napoleone, 1810-1895; Longfellow, Henry Wadsworth, 1807-1882; Dante Alighieri, 1265-1321
- [illegible] to [Gallenga, Antonio M.]Bramcote, England, 1845 September 24; 6 pages (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 59)
  Regards the author's efforts to write a volume about or translation of Dante's works, with which Gallenga has agreed to help him. Mention is also made of a volume of sermons published by the author. The postscript includes updates from the author's bookseller.
  Ms 617(1 and 2)
  Gallenga, Antonio Carlo Napoleone, 1810-1895; Dante Alighieri, 1265-1321
- Pepoli, Carlo to Mariotti, L.[illegible], 2 pages; Pepoli, Carlo, conte, 1796-1881 (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 60)
  Mentions some articles that he wrote for the publication "Old Monthly," complaining about the mediocre pay. Extends an open invitation to Mariotti to visit him and his wife. Second page includes [librarian's] handwritten specification that the letter's signee is "Count [Carlo] Pepoli." ("Mariotti" was the adopted name of the Italian literary scholar Antonio Gallenga.)
  Ms 618
- Pepoli, Carlo to Gallenga, Antonio M., 1 page; Pepoli, Carlo, conte, 1796-1881 (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 61)
  Makes plans to have lunch with Gallenga. Discusses a project, in part executed by the writer and critic James Henry Leigh Hunt, to research the history of several families, including Pepoli's own.
  Ms 619
  Gallenga, Antonio Carlo Napoleone, 1810-1895; Hunt, Leigh, 1784-1859
- Mazzini, Giuseppe to Gallenga, Antonio M., 1847 September; 3 pages; Mazzini, Giuseppe, 1805-1872 (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 62)
  Reports on developments in Italy, including movements of Swiss troops and events in Sicily. Insists that in order to help the situation, money must be raised. Reference is made to a certain Townsend. Gallenga was an Italian literary scholar living in England at the time and involved in garnering support for Italian revolutionary efforts in England. The letter is one of about nine or ten from Mazzini to Gallenga that, according to a librarian's note added to the scrapbook, appeared in H. Nelson Gay's 1928 pamphlet, Mazzini e Antonio Gallenga apostoli dell'indipendenza italiana in Inghilterra. Gay is responsible for having dated the letter.
  Ms 620
- Mazzini, Giuseppe to Mariotti, L., 1844 August or September; 1 page; Mazzini, Giuseppe, 1805-1872 (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 62)
  Regards a letter to be sent from London to Paris connected to Italian revolutionary efforts. Mazzini is writing to "Mariotti," the adopted name of Antonio Gallenga, an Italian literary scholar living in England and involved in garnering support for Italian revolutionary efforts in England. The letter is one of about nine or ten from Mazzini to Gallenga that, according to a librarian's note added to the scrapbook, appeared in H. Nelson Gay's 1928 pamphlet, Mazzini e Antonio Gallenga apostoli dell'indipendenza italiana in Inghilterra. Gay is responsible for having dated the letter.
  Ms 621
- Joseph Mazzini. Not Garibaldi, but He, Italy's "Man of Men, Her Real Liberator"New York, NY, 2743; 1 page; Morais, Henry S. (Henry Samuel), 1860-1935 (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 62)
  Editorial submitted to the New York Times by Henry S. Morais, an Italian-American, insisting (against a claim made by the Times in an earlier article) upon the credit Mazzini deserves for helping to liberate and unify Italy.
- Nelson Gay, H. to Stillwell, Margaret Bingham Axenfels, Brunnen, Switzerland, 10448; 2 pages; Gay, H. Nelson (Harry Nelson), 1870-1932 (Box 10, Volume 4, Pages 62-63, tucked between pages)
  Announces the publication of H. Nelson Gay's Mazzini e Antonio Gallenga, which Gay published using photographs of the correspondence between Mazzini and Gallenga preserved at the Annmary Brown Memory. Nelson Gay is sending a copy of the publication to Stillwell. He further reflects on the difficulty of dating the letters and on their importance for locating Gallenga in "the history of the period."
  Stillwell, Margaret Bingham, 1887-1984; Gallenga, Antonio M.; Mazzini, Giuseppe
- Mazzini, Giuseppe to Mariotti, L., 1844 July 5; 3 pages; Mazzini, Giuseppe, 1805-1872 (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 63)
  Written in response to a letter from Mariotti. Regards efforts to garner support for Italian revolutionary efforts in England. References are made to rising "agitazioni," a certain "comitato," and a petition that Mazzini is circulating. The "Mariotti" to whom Mazzini writes was the adopted name of Antonio Gallenga, an Italian literary scholar living in England at the time. The letter is one of about nine or ten from Mazzini to Gallenga that, according to a librarian's note added to the scrapbook, appeared in H. Nelson Gay's 1928 pamphlet, Mazzini e Antonio Gallenga apostoli dell'indipendenza italiana in Inghilterra. Gay is responsible for having dated the letter.
  Ms 622
  Gallenga, Antonio Carlo Napoleone, 1810-1895; Gay, H. Nelson (Harry Nelson), 1870-1932
- Mazzini, Giuseppe to Mariotti, L.London, England, 1845 May 17?; 3 pages; Mazzini, Giuseppe, 1805-1872 (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 63)
  Regards the creation of a public English associatoin for the Nazionalità Italiana. Mazzini is writing to "Mariotti," the adopted name of Antonio Gallenga, an Italian literary scholar living in England at the time and involved in garnering English support for Italian revolutionary efforts. The letter is one of about nine or ten from Mazzini to Gallenga that, according to a librarian's note added to the scrapbook, appeared in H. Nelson Gay's 1928 pamphlet, Mazzini e Antonio Gallenga apostoli dell'indipendenza italiana in Inghilterra. Gay is responsible for having dated the letter.
  Ms 623
- Mazzini, Giuseppe to Mariotti, L.London, England, 1845 October 20?; 3 pages; Mazzini, Giuseppe, 1805-1872 (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 64)
  Regards correspondences about Mazzini and Mariotti's efforts to garner support for Italian revolutionary efforts in England. Mazzini offers advice about how to speak to the English. "Mariotti" was the adopted name of Antonio Gallenga, an Italian literary scholar living in Italy at the time. The letter is one of about nine or ten from Mazzini to Gallenga that, according to a librarian's note added to the scrapbook, appeared in H. Nelson Gay's 1928 pamphlet, Mazzini e Antonio Gallenga apostoli dell'indipendenza italiana in Inghilterra. Gay is responsible for having dated the letter.
  Ms 624
- Mazzini, Giuseppe to Mariotti, L., 1845 April 26; 2 pages; Mazzini, Giuseppe, 1805-1872 (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 64)
  Regards press coverage of revolutionary efforts in Italy. The "Mariotti" to whom Mazzini writes was the adopted name of Antonio Gallenga, an Italian literary scholar living in England at the time. The letter is one of about nine or ten from Mazzini to Gallenga that, according to a librarian's note added to the scrapbook, appeared in H. Nelson Gay's 1928 pamphlet, Mazzini e Antonio Gallenga apostoli dell'indipendenza italiana in Inghilterra. Gay is responsible for having dated the letter.
  Ms 625
- Mazzini, Giuseppe to Mariotti, L., 1844 June 8; 1 page; Mazzini, Giuseppe, 1805-1872 (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 65)
  Regards some difficulty surrounding a book or pamphlet: Mazzini speaks about bringing the affair into public. The postscript of the letter asks for information regarding a certain Townsend. "Mariotti" was the adopted name of Antonio Gallenga, an Italian literary scholar living in Italy at the time, involved in garnering support for Italian revolutionary efforts in Italy. The letter is one of about nine or ten from Mazzini to Gallenga that, according to a librarian's note added to the scrapbook, appeared in H. Nelson Gay's 1928 pamphlet, Mazzini e Antonio Gallenga apostoli dell'indipendenza italiana in Inghilterra. Gay is responsible for having dated the letter.
  Ms 626
- Mazzini, Giuseppe to Mariotti, L.London, England, 3 pages; Mazzini, Giuseppe, 1805-1872 (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 65)
  Writing in reference to an article published in the London Herald, Mazzini shares his observations about efforts to raise support for Italian revolutionary efforts in England. ("Mariotti" was the adopted name of Antonio Gallenga, an Italian literary scholar living in England at the time.) Mazzini speaks of the danger of arousing "l'amor proprio inglese contro di noi!" but ultimately expresses his faith that the battle can be won. The letter is one of about nine or ten from Mazzini to Gallenga that, according to a librarian's note added to the scrapbook, appeared in H. Nelson Gay's 1928 pamphlet, Mazzini e Antonio Gallenga apostoli dell'indipendenza italiana in Inghilterra.
  Ms 627
- Mazzini, Giuseppe to Mariotti, L., 1844 December 6?; 1 page; Mazzini, Giuseppe, 1805-1872 (Box 10, Volume 4, Page 66)
  Mazzini asks Mariotti to translate the enclosed article for him into Italian, which he will then try to have published in the "Chronicles." ("Mariotti" was the adopted name of the Italian literary scholar Antonio Gallenga, living in England at the time and involved in garnering support for Italian revolutionary efforts in England.) The letter is one of about nine or ten from Mazzini to Gallenga that, according to a librarian's note added to the scrapbook, appeared in H. Nelson Gay's 1928 pamphlet, Mazzini e Antonio Gallenga apostoli dell'indipendenza italiana in Inghilterra. Gay is responsible for having dated the letter.
  Ms 628